[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a sutta from the Samyutta Nikaya and it's in regards to celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this conversation takes place between a king and a bhikkhu named Venerable Pindola.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the king goes up to this monk and he asks him, what is the cause and the reason
[SPEAKER_00]: Why these other young monks, these bhikkhus, young boys with black hair, endowed with the blessing of youth, in the prime of their life, who have not played with sensual pleasures, lead the complete and pure holy life, all their lives, and maintain it continuously.
[SPEAKER_00]: And venerable Pindola, he answers, great king, this was said by the blessed one who knows and sees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come bhikkhus, towards women old enough to be your mother, set up the idea that they are your mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards those of an age to be your sisters, set up the idea that they are your sisters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards those young enough to be your daughters, set up the idea that they are your daughters.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the cause and the reason why these young bhikkhus lead the complete and pure holy life all their lives and maintain it continuously.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the King says, the mind is wanton, so, you know, given to lust, unsatisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes states of lust arise even towards women old enough to be one's mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes they arise towards women of an age to be one's sister or one's daughter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any cause and reason why these young bhikkhus lead the complete... Is there any other cause and reason why these young bhikkhus lead a complete and pure holy life, all their lives, and maintain it continuously?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he gives the other, a few other causes, but just this reason first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person has to, you know, consider
[SPEAKER_00]: Other people as, you know, your mother, your father, your brother, your sister, your friend, your son, your daughter, so as to maybe give you a sense of shame or make you a bit more respectful and not see them in that light of a sexual partner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but see, as it says, you know, they would establish an idea
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, they would set up a context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in order to be able for that idea to become a context that will prevent you to have a lust arising, you need to have been withdrawn and centrally restrained already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the mind need to have developed to some extent, because otherwise people might have an idea, they will ask for the duration of the thought, and then the context goes with the thought, where the idea is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the lust comes back and takes over and becomes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's something you need to frequently think about, pondering, when you're not lustful, and develop that as a as a state of mind, that whomever you are relating to, is through these frameworks of mother, sister, daughter, friend, like the compassion, same, it's kind of similar to the Brahma-Vihāras, you set up a state of mind through, like, frequently recollecting and thinking about it, up until those values are established, and then they need to be protected, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you expect to just have this idea magically take over you, and then prevent lust from arising, just because you thought of it that way, no, there won't be lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: My lust initially is a novelty of a new thing, but then, it's just going to become dry abstraction, where you try to force yourself to think, but, like, lust is still there first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person might be lustful towards another person, and then,
[SPEAKER_00]: They think, well, let me consider this person who I'm lusting after as my mother.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's just going to be, as I said, trying to manage the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to be recognizing that the state of lust, the lustful mind, should not be acted out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the lust is not present, you know, when you haven't acted out of it, it will have to subside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you start pondering and, and, and, you know, recognize the danger in it, and establishing the ideas that can help you, then later not have... last not arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not just... it's not on the level of an antidote.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of developing your mind even before the lust is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, in order to to set up the idea that can then endure as a context that will prevent you to be lustful towards this person or that person, you need to have seen your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to have understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to have been practicing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a certain order of the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, yeah, I did it, I can make sense of it, let me just do it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be doing it for wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and people exactly would be trying to pace and almost maintain these thoughts, like, mechanically, as a mantra, to not have lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's not setting up the idea, as it's written in the scribes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the dhamma, the presence of the phenomenon of...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the framework where people will be regarded in such manner, which is
[SPEAKER_01]: Not conducive for lust, not increasing and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you put the lust first, then, yeah, even mother, sister, daughter, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind will be attracted through lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to have, you know, restraint beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making that decision, having difficulty with it, getting some benefit, clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you need to practice towards the right view first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, everything else would be just rooted in you mistaking the practice of dhamma, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: uprooting of the existence and the problem, for managing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this would be just another novelty way to manage these disturbing states of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can see that this is for just helping a developed mind already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind, that's, that's, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Already has right view, so now...
[SPEAKER_01]: Person that sees the mind, for what it is, then can relate to it in the right manner, not act out of it and try to manage it, but actually can endure it in order to approach it, as we say so often.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then such ideas, perceptions, contemplations, themes, of course, they are very beneficial, because they'll be done on the right basis for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: It helps to sort of clean the mind in broad, you know, just covering all bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that one can live the celibate life fully.
[SPEAKER_00]: One's whole life, as it says, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as this king says, he says, the mind is so, you know, wanton, that even
[SPEAKER_00]: It can have attraction to the mother, the daughter, the... Because the last will be put first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The last of mine will be first.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the ideas will be secondary abstractions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he says, what other reason do these monks live such a good holy life, complete?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, eh... Great King, this was said by the Blessed One, because we view this very body upwards from the soles of the feet, downwards from the tips of the hairs, enclosed in skin,
[SPEAKER_00]: As full of many kinds of impurities, there are these... there are in this body head hairs, sinews, flesh, bone, contents of the stomach, excrement and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, before we go further, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, review this.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, people often confuse that as do the body sweeping of this visualizations and so on and sensations of head to toe.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Review those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see insides of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, review them reflexively, because those are factual things that your body is made of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, it's another context that you established, another set of ideas that is suitable and not... that is suitable for non-lust and not suitable for lust, if established correctly in the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even then, people would do these reviewings and so on, on the level of, just like, as I said, abstract ideas of brain, bile, this, this, almost like mantra chanting, the same, as they would do in the monasteries.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, that's not reviewing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not seeing it on the right level, that you are having already, you've already taken this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through your ownership of the body, then start reflecting of that body that you own, mistakenly, sure, but the mistake is real as such, as made out of these things, so that you experience this passion towards what you own.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just some random kind of Abhidhamma commentary style of just... just go through the list of what the body is and repeat it, and somehow it's purifying your mind on some invisible subconscious levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the one... the main problem for giving into lust and engaging with objects of your sense perceptions is that you're taking this body as yours, pleasurable, agreeable, suitable, accessible to get pleasure through and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Friendly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: In your favor.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not any of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you can, again, if you don't see your mind, if you don't have the right view, all of this will be just another way of managing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be just telling to yourself what the body is, and it will have like a partial result, as I said, of the novelty, but sooner or later you get used to it, and the last comes back first, and nothing has really changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to do it on that level of not like, oh, I'm doing these observations of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to see what your body is, as in your experience as a whole,
[SPEAKER_01]: What is this body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like what I observe on account of already having the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the necessary basis for my observation of anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: The flesh, the brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the presence of this thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do I have to look at the characteristic?
[SPEAKER_01]: See, by understanding what your body is in this manner, you're actually seeing the signs of your mind already, because that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that background, it's that peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: That cannot be... that which cannot be directly attended to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, through body object, so to speak, you are still doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still actually uncovering the characteristics of that enduring mind, which is inseparate from the enduring body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, review it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't leave any part of it as
[SPEAKER_01]: Of that basis, for the world that you perceive, for the desires that you have, for the joys and miseries and so on, don't leave any basis of that background, enduring body that you are here and now, don't leave any of that basis that's not thoroughly reflected upon as not yours, not suitable, a dart filled with impurities and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you do to that extent, the last will still have a footing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can reflect on other people's body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, on that peripheral, concrete basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as a second-hand kind of abstraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you reflect on other people's bodies, it's so that, again, you're seeing yourself through the same form.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't leave that part out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't leave yourself out when reflecting on other bodies.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep that that correct relationship between your point of view and the body you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not taking it as an observation method or an observation object.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're taking it as a reflection theme that undermines your point of view of ownership that regards this body gratuitously as pleasant and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a very different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would go about it very differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Sutta goes on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Bhikkhu says, you know, reflect on your... review your body, these different parts and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the King says,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is quite easy for those bhikkhus who are developed in body, developed in virtue, developed in mind, developed in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is it difficult for those bhikkhus who are undeveloped in body, virtue, mind and wisdom?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, though one thinks I will attend to the body as foul, as disgusting, one beholds it as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any other reason why these young bhikkhus lead the complete and pure holy life all their lives?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's said there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's possible for those that are developed in virtue and the body and the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, then you will again...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's quite a dangerous inversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything is... Like, that's what I mean, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless people realize what comes first and the right view comes first, the virtue, sense restraint, solitude and the right view come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, you'll be taking things that don't apply to you
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't have the right view and thinking you are practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, it's quite dangerous because, again, why would you then look on how to start practicing the dhamma, I get the right view, when you're already thinking of and have a view that you're practicing the dhamma by doing all these things that you read in the suttas and there's so many of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that other sutta with that monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's in a cemetery, in that charnel ground, where they're burning bodies, and he sees a discarded body of a young woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... as he was there reflecting on the body, he became lustful towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like he was... he was seeing, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like they had a super practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're staring at dead bodies and so on, and then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it needs to be done on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be done on the level of the context of what am I doing, not on the level of I will just look at this and that will do the work for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, when you get there, maybe the shocking value of something, of something you don't want to look at, but again, the mind with lust, mind not freed from lust, will get used to it, will get used to anything, and will then perpetuate its lust towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's endless, because it's the framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in the things you're looking or avoiding from looking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the attitude of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what you put first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in desire for pleasure and not seeing the danger of it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ask, is there another reason why these monks keep celibate?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what the Blessed One said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus dwell guarding the doors of the sense faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having seen a form of the eye, do not grasp at its signs and features, since if you leave the eye-faculty unguarded, evil, unwholesome states of covetousness and displeasure might invade you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practice the way of its restraint."
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he just goes on saying, well, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that he keeps basically lowering the bar, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Firstly, it was just the context of how to regard people.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might be attracted to sustain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, okay, yeah, but that's too much to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else can a person who can't do that do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, take the context of your own body as foul, as repulsive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, okay, but even that is a bit too much to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, how else to leave the celibate life happy and so on, if you can't quite do that yet?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, God descends those.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is like lowering the requirements, so to speak, but even then, yeah, God descends doors, so that signs and features... See, you don't attend to signs and features, you don't see signs and features, you see the thing with your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has its sort of significance, implications, signs and features, these peripheral ideas that come with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what you don't grasp wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you don't let become your context carelessly and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't grasp those signs and features.
[SPEAKER_01]: Provocative lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you would recognize that's where the problem is, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the lust is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you guard the door so that these signs and features will be not overwhelming you and so that you can actually understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you need to stop looking at things that have provocative signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can stop chasing them, stop going after them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're seeing things in different light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eventually, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, as, oh, this woman is like my mother.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you are, you're kind of, I'm perverting that order of seeing, of putting what your lust wants first, the context that lust sets up first, then, yes, you could realize, oh, yeah, I could just sustain these thoughts, think about these thoughts, and the mind will go into that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by that point, you're already seeing the mind, and mind is on the level of the signs and features, not on the level of, as I said so many times, what you're observing with your senses, including your own thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the king, after that, he says, oh, it's wonderful.
[SPEAKER_00]: How well this has been stated by the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the cause and reason why these young monks, with the blessing of youth and the prime of their life, have not played with sensual pleasures and lead the complete, pure, holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, in my case too, when I enter my hāram, unguarded in body, speech and mind, without setting up mindfulness, the context, unrestrained in the sense faculties, on that occasion states of lust assail me forcefully.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when I enter my hāram, guarded in body, speech and mind, with the context set up, mindfulness set up, restrained in the sense faculties, on that occasion states of lust do not assail me in such a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so even King had some wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: While he was still living with his wives, he had some wisdom there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To see for himself, yeah, what the root, what the root of the lust is, what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's guarded mind or unguarded mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the higher.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not the objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's not the objects, yeah.